Today's דף Daf is י"ט, Yud Tet, we are going to continue
to talk about some of the practical aspects of שחיטה. Shechita. Yesterday
we had learned, we had been discussing the problem of הגרמה, Hagrama,
which is moving the knife outside of the שחיטה Shechita zone, which
means above the top ring cartilage ring, I think it's cartilage, top
ring in the trachea. And we had learned that רב Rav and
שמואל Shmuel had a certain problem with הגרמה Hagrama that others did
not have. Not clear what it was, for now we'll do רש"י
Rashi's explanation that they didn't like to שחט Shecht in the ring
itself, they only wanted for the other rings, they only wanted the
שחיטה Shechita in the space between the rings. Anyway, and the גמרא
Gemara spoke about a number of people that did not agree to
רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, and it ended with interesting discussions about
keeping the practices of the place that you leave when you go
to a different place when you go to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
and a respect for a range of different practices, which is a
very important phrase used in general to talk about a respect for
different practices within הלכה, Halacha, נהרא נהרא ופשטיה, Nara Nara u'pashtei, every
river goes according to its, you know, to where it spreads, and
a respect that it all comes from the same river but in
different locales the practices are different. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
continues. רבי שמעון בן לקיש, Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish, it is the
word לקיש, Lakish, it is seven lines before the lines get wide
or eight lines.
Yeah, תוספות, Tosafot, yeah, exactly. So שמעון לקיש אמר בחודא דכובעא. Shimon
Lakish amar bechuda de'kova. So רבי שמעון בן לקיש Rabbi Shimon ben
Lakish said that the שחיטה Shechita could even be good if it
was in the tip of the hat. So what's the hat? So
if you look here, right, here's the nice little picture again. So
you see this whole thing is like a hat, right? And it's
sort of especially your side view, you see it's sort of even
at the top it's sort of comes up at an angle, a
little bit of an angle, it's sort of, you know, there's sort
of like a rise and a tip. So he allowed the שחיטה
Shechita to be even way up here, because the question is going
to be way up here. Sounds like...
yeah, even above
the flower.
Apparently, right, above the ring,
yeah, apparently that's what this, this fleshy area here, if I'm understanding
correctly, is what's being referred to as the tip of the hat.
Now the question is, you know, that even when we're allowing higher
than, you know, in the top ring and basically what we're going
to see is if you remember there was a position of רבי
חנינא בן אנטיגנוס Rabbi Chanina ben Antigonus that said that הגרמה Hagrama
is not a problem, which is going to be interpreted to mean
not that הגרמה Hagrama is not a problem at all, but it's
going to be interpreted to mean that, you know, that there, that
high, that you can go higher than the other opinions. So the
question is going to be how high. And that's really going to
be the framing of a lot of today's discussion from רבי חנינא
בן אנטיגנוס Rabbi Chanina ben Antigonus who allows you even higher than
this ring itself, you know, what about higher. And if I understand
רש"י Rashi correctly, just so you understand, just so we're looking at
the same picture, you see here right after this ring here begins
at the very bottom of it, you see here there are some
ligaments or whatever, some muscles in the middle of that space, can
you sort of see that? So the question is going to be,
can you cut in the ligaments of that space or does it
have to be in the bone directly underneath, you know, underneath it.
How high can that go? Okay, or could it be even top
on top of those ligaments. So anyway ריש לקיש Reish Lakish allowed
even cutting at the top of this whole structure. Okay and that
is going to be rejected. So let's take a look.
Where do they actually really do it practically today?
I mean, they obviously don't שחט Shecht that high. That high is
somewhere like here. You know, they שחט Shecht more like here, you
know, a few inches down. Okay but again I don't know for
sure.
Yeah those go higher than that's a cutaway, so they go all
the way up, even in the illustration today.
Yeah they go even up here. So again it's not exactly clear
to me. There's going to be a question about cutting in some
of these like, you know, fleshy areas. It's not clear to me
whether we mean this bottom fleshy area or the top one, I
have to be honest, I'm not exactly sure.
But let's take a look. So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish did it
at the very top.
So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish did it at the very top and
the גמרא Gemara says, I'm sorry I'm trying to multitask here, get
this started right time.
Okay so the גמרא Gemara says,
okay,
so קרי עליה רבי יוחנן, Karei aleih Rabbi Yochanan, so רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan said on him גיסא גיסא, Gisa Gisa, like too much,
too much, you know, even if we allow higher, higher than the,
than the, than the very top cartilage, the top ring, that's too
high. אמר רב פפא משמיה דרבא, Amar Rav Pappa mishmeih de'Rava, פגע
בחיטי טרפה. paga be'chiti tereifa. Now it's the issue I'm, I was
talking about which is these strings. This more like fleshy area here,
not the bone area.
And again what's not clear to me, yeah, what's not clear to
me, I have to admit, is whether we mean this area here
or this area up here. It sounds like in all honesty that
again
I'm not really sure, it sounds like
that ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said even way up here and now
we're talking about this zone here. So it's not clear to me
whether we mean this zone or this zone. Okay so anyway the
argument is that if you touch those rings, those strings, it's a
טרפה. tereifa. So איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu, so the question was
raised what.
Yeah, the picture here is not as good.
Yeah, yeah, it's totally unusable here.
Yeah, it's not great, but the little I can make out from
this figure makes it sound like we are talking about these top
this top area. That we're assuming in here is כשר, kasher, ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish שחט shechted even up here and now the question
is what about this space, the space about this these muscled giller
area right over there. Okay, so פגע בחיטי כשרה. paga be-chite ksheira.
So, איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu, so the question was raised: פגע ונגע
בהן, paga ve-naga ba-hen, did פגע paga mean that you touch them,
דכתיב, dichtiv, ויפגע בו וימת, vayifga bo vayamos, that he encountered him
and he died, which means he like, you know, he smote him.
או דילמא פגע ולא נגע, o dilma paga velo naga, or it
means that you didn't touch, דכתיב ויפגעו בו מלאכי אלוהים, dichtiv vayifge'u
vo mal'achei Elokim, the angels of God encountered, but it didn't mean
that they actually touched him. Okay, so what's the question? So I'm
going to read it like רש"י Rashi says, actually it's a debate
of רש"י Rashi and תוספות. Tosafot. So the way that רש"י Rashi
says is, I mean not רש"י, Rashi, תוספות, Tosafot, which is the
simpler read, is are we assuming that it's when you cut anywhere
in this area it's כשרה, ksheira, that's פגע ונגע? paga ve-naga? Or
no, anywhere in this area is okay, it's only if you cut
above the area and you don't touch, but above the area it's
טרפה, treifa, but the area itself you're okay. So that's the question.
Okay, so let's take a look.
אתמר אמר רב פפא משמיה דרבא: itmar amar Rav Papa mishmeih de-Rava:
שיור בחיטי כשרה, shiyur be-chite ksheira, as
long as you leave some of the strings over it's כשר, kasher,
which means you can cut through that stringy muscular area as long
as you don't cut above it. אמר רבא מימר, amar Rava meimar,
so that says that פגע paga means פגע ולא נגע, paga velo
naga, that it's only a problem when you cut above it, you
encounter without touching, but if you cut through them actually that's low
enough and that's okay. אמר רב מימר בר מר ינוקא, amar Rav
Meimar bar Mar Yenuka, what?
אמר, amar, right, so מר מימר, Mar Meimar, the son of מר
ינוקא, Mar Yenuka, the child says: הוי קאימנא קמיה דרב חייא בריה
דרב אוויא, havei ka'imna kameih de-Rav Chiya breih de-Rav Avya, I was
standing in front of רב חייא Rav Chiya the son of רב
אוויא, Rav Avya, ואמר לי, va-amar li, and he said to me:
שיור בחיטי כשרה, shiyur be-chite ksheira, same point, as long as you
leave some of that stringy area it's כשר, kasher, meaning if you
cut through it and not above it you're okay. אמר ליה רבינא
לרב אשי: amar leih Ravina le-Rav Ashi: אמר לי רב שמן מסוברא,
amar li Rav Sheman mi-Suvra, so רב שמן
מסוברא Rav Sheman mi-Suvra said to me: איקלע מר זוטרא לאתרין, ikla
Mar Zutra le-asran, מר זוטרא Mar Zutra came to our place, ודרש,
ve-darash, and he extrapolated the following or expounded on the following: שיור
בחיטי כשרה, shiyur be-chite ksheira, same point, if you leave over some
of that string area you're okay. מר בר רב אשי אמר, Mar
bar Rav Ashi amar, מר בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi
says: פגע בחיטי כשרה שיור
בחיטי טריפה. paga be-chite ksheira shiyur be-chite treifa. Now by the way
רש"י Rashi switched the גרסא, girsa, so we're going to, we're reading
this according to תוספות, Tosafot, we're going to go back to תוספות's
Tosafot גרסא, girsa, and תוספות's Tosafot גרסא girsa had this reversed. שיור
בחיטי כשרה, shiyur be-chite ksheira, if you leave over some of the
stringy area it's okay, meaning if you cut through that more muscular
area. פגע בחיטי, paga be-chite, which again for תוספות Tosafot means you
cut above that string area,
טרפה. treifa. והלכתא, ve-hilchata, the ruling is: משיפוע כובע ולמטה כשרה, mi-shipu'a
kova u-lemata ksheira, it's only כשרה ksheira from the slanting of the
of the of the cap. So again I believe we're talking about
this cap, so not the top of this cap right over here,
it's only where this cap begins to slant, only from that point
below is it כשרה, ksheira, not the top of the cap itself
which is where ריש לקיש Reish Lakish did it. והיינו דשיור בחיטי,
ve-hainu de-shiyur be-chite, that's assuming that actually you're cutting through the string
area below it, the muscular area below it. If you're cutting completely
above the muscular area it's not good. So basically what we're saying
is, as opposed to the two opinions in the משנה Mishna that
basically only allowed you to cut up to about here, the ring,
the very top ring and said anywhere above that was no good
and that was הגרמה. hagrama. Now we're following the position of who
was it? רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס Rabbi Chanina ben Antigonus who really
says there's no הגרמה, hagrama, which doesn't literally mean no הגרמה hagrama
but really means this whole area is okay as long as you
don't get to the very top. Where's the bottom area? Oh, the
bottom goes to the lungs. I think all the way up to
the lungs, but that's not being discussed here, it's in a תוספתא.
Tosefta. Okay, so now let's just try to finish let me give
this one last try here. I'm sorry about this, it's just too
bad for
me
and unable to connect, so now it's a problem
with my connection.
It might be נהגא דשחיטה? nahaga de-shechita? This?
You know of שחיטה? shechita?
No.
I'll leave that to the professionals.
Make
the vegetarians out of
us.
Sorry everybody one second.
I don't know if he's still on, he would have called me
though. Alright whatever, let's keep on going.
So anyway the גמרא Gemara continues: רב נחמן אכשר משיפוע כובע ולמטה.
Rav Nachman achshar mi-shipu'a kova u-lemata. So רב נחמן Rav Nachman again
allowed the שחיטה shechita anywhere from the from the... The angling of
the cap, which is the very top and below.
I mean you could ask why the editor put the הלכתא hilchosa
before that. Oh, okay. I don't know. אמר ליה רב חנן בר
רב קטינא—so amar lei Rav Chanan bar Rav Kitina anyway, אמר ליה
רב חנן בר רב קטינא לרב נחמן—so amar lei Rav Chanan bar
Rav Kitina le-Rav Nachman רב... Rav oh, finally!
Oh, Jed is still there? I don't know why he didn't call
to tell us that it wasn't on.
Maybe he could see?
No, everything was off. He could have stuck through it to see.
Alright, here we go, finally.
Okay, adjust
this computer bit there, that doesn't necessarily...
that's a good point. He usually calls me with
problems.
Optimizer of...
Okay, finally. Alright, let's take a look. רב נחמן's Rav Nachman from
again, from the top of יט עמוד א. yud-tes amud aleph. רב
נחמן Rav Nachman אמר משיפור כובע ולמטה. amar mishipur kova u'lemata. רב
נחמן Rav Nachman allowed it from the tilting of the cap and
below, meaning where it starts angling at the very top. אמר ליה
רב חנן בר רב קטינא לרב נחמן: amar lei Rav Chanan bar
Rav Kitina le-Rav Nachman: כמאן? ke-man? Who are you going like? Now
what we're doing is we're exploring, okay, we just ruled this way,
but how does it fit in our מתניתין? matnitin? לא כרבנן ולא
כרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. lo k'rabbanan v'lo k'Rebbi Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda. It's
not like the רבנן Rabbanan and not like רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה,
Rebbi Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda, because they say anywhere above the top ring—this
is a whole structure above the top ring—they say, right, anywhere above
this top ring right
here is no good and you're allowing this entire structure. So who
are you going like? אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back to
him: אנא לא חילק ידענא ולא בילק ידענא אנא שמעתא ידענא. ana
lo chilek yadana v'lo bilek yadana ana shma'ta yadana. I don't know
חילק, chilek, I don't know בילק, bilek, I know my teaching. So
what's חילק chilek and בילק? bilek? רש"י Rashi says based on a
גמרא, Gemara, so first רש"י Rashi tries a creative read which wasn't
his own, it's actually in רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom already, that חילק
chilek was רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה—I'm Rebbi Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda sorry, חילק
chilek was the רבנן Rabbanan that said you have to cut through
like לחלוק lachlok the entire top ring, you can't go up even
for, remember,
move your knife above it even for a part of it. And
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rebbi Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda was בילק, bilek, which
means somehow to like make a mess of things or to do
things not straight, because he allowed you to go up near the
end. But רש"י Rashi says in the end that's not what it
means. These are just phrases. It's like saying, I don't know Joe,
I don't know Schmoe, I just know my tradition. So don't talk
to me about רבי יוסי, Rebbi Yose, don't talk to me about
the רבנן, Rabbanan, I know this is the tradition. Okay? אנא לא
חילק ידענא ולא בילק ידענא אנא שמעתא ידענא. ana lo chilek yadana
v'lo bilek yadana ana shma'ta yadana. I know my tradition דאמר רבי
חייא בר זבדא אמר רבי חנינא ואמרי לה אמר רבי יעקב בר
אידי אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, d'amar Rebbi Chiya bar Zavda amar
Rebbi Chanina v'amrei lah amar Rebbi Yaakov bar Idi amar Rebbi Yehoshua
ben Levi, that we have this tradition and אמורא amora tradition: משיפור
כובע ולמטה כשרה. mishipur kova u'lemata ksheira. From the angling of the
cap and below it's כשרה. ksheira. I don't know how it fits
into the משנה, Mishnah, but that's what I know.
That's what I know.
Right? I don't even know who said it, but that's the tradition
that from the slanting of the cap and below it's כשרה. ksheira.
Okay. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי: amar Rebbi Yehoshua ben Levi: מוגרמת
דרבנן כשרה לרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. mugremes d'rabbanan ksheira l'Rebbi Yose b'Rebbi
Yehuda. Now we're going to actually explain how it fits in. מוגרמת
Yehuda. What's הגרמה hagrama for the רבנן? Rabbanan? Remember, הגרמה hagrama for
the רבנן Rabbanan is you could be doing the
first half correctly or the first ninety percent correctly, but if you
go up to right above the line of the top ring, it's
not good. That רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rebbi Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda says
is good, obviously that's the debate. כשרה לרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. ksheira
l'Rebbi Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda. What רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rebbi Yose b'Rebbi
Yehuda would say is not good if the entire שחיטה shechita was
above the top ring,
then he would agree that that's not good. But what's not good
for him, כשרה לרבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס. ksheira l'Rebbi Chanina ben Antigonus.
That's כשרה ksheira according to רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס, Rebbi Chanina ben
Antigonus, which is basically now putting in the framework of the positions
of the תנאים tannaim and saying the position of רבי חנינא בן
אנטיגנוס Rebbi Chanina ben Antigonus who at least the way it was
articulated was he rejected
הגרמה. hagrama. Now we're not saying he rejected הגרמה, hagrama, we're just
saying that he allows a lot more of the neck for the
act of שחיטה. shechita. So he would allow what רבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה Rebbi Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda does not allow. פשיטא! pishita! Obviously! מהו
דתימא, mahu d'teima, you
might have said, רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס עד דרבנן קאי, Rebbi Chanina
ben Antigonus ad derabbanan ka-ei, maybe רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס Rebbi Chanina
ben Antigonus who's rejecting הגרמה hagrama is only rejecting the רבנן's Rabbanan
הגרמה, hagrama, not maybe he's not rejecting רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rebbi
Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda, maybe he's not being more lenient than רבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה. Rebbi Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda. קא משמע לן ka mashma lan
that he's rejecting even רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rebbi Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda,
he's being more lenient than everybody. ואימא הכי נמי? v'eima hachi nami?
Maybe that is the right read? Maybe he's only being more lenient
than the רבנן? Rabbanan? אם כן היד עליה מיבעי ליה. im ken
heid alei mibai lei. It should have said that רבי חנינא בן
אנטיגנוס Rebbi Chanina ben Antigonus when quoted him yesterday, it should have
said he testified on it, on הגרמה. hagrama. When it says that
רבי יוסי בר חנינא Rebbi Yose bar Chanina testified about הגרמה hagrama
and it repeated the phrase about הגרמה, hagrama, it means anybody's definition
about הגרמה, hagrama, he was lenient about. So he said what you
guys are saying is הגרמה hagrama is not הגרמה hagrama at all,
for him you have a much larger space to do the שחיטה
shechita in.
Okay, so start in that in the box?
What? No. The רבנן Rabbanan and רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rebbi Yose
b'Rebbi Yehuda said you have to start down here and the only
question was could you move up towards the end? Right. He says
all of your guys' הגרמה hagrama is not a problem for me,
I allow all this entire space.
So you have to start in the ring?
No, you don't. As long as you don't start at the cap.
So you can start...
Yeah, you can start way over here. Exactly. Yep. Okay.
Is רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס Rebbi Chanina ben Antigonus the same as
אנטיגנוס איש סוכו?
Antigonus Ish Socho? I don't know.
the angling of the cap below, that's only consistent obviously with this
position, not with the position of the Rabbis. Now fine, now that
we're done with that and I'm hoping that I have identified for
you the exact correct places, you know, anatomically, I can't promise that
I have. But anyway now we are going to get to more
interesting, for me at least, conceptual questions of exactly what the debate
is. So let's take a look. אמר רב הונא אמר רב אסי,
Amar Rav Huna amar Rav Assi, Rav Huna said in the name
of Rav Assi. מחלוקת בששחט שני שליש והגרים שליש. Machlokes b'sheshachat shenei
shlish v'higrim shlish. This is what we've been assuming. We're back to
the debate of the רבנן Rabbanan and רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. Rebbi
Yossi b'Rebbi Yehuda. Okay, and the question was you messed up after
you did the majority. So he's saying the debate is when you
did the first two-thirds correctly and the last third you moved your
knife, you know, higher than the place of the שחיטה. shechita. But
the first two-thirds was correct. By the way, just remember again that
we're talking about depth, right? You're not talking about like two-thirds, you
know, cutting into it and then whatever. We're talking about how deep
you're cutting in. You cut in because the שחיטה shechita is defined
as cutting in the majority depth of the actual trachea. So you
cut in two-thirds into the trachea and then the last part you
did above, you did too high. Okay, so that's the debate. דרבנן
סברי כולי שחיטה בעינן בטבעת גדולה, DeRabbanan savri kulei shechita ba'inan b'tabaas
gedola, the Rabbis hold you need the entire שחיטה shechita in this
upper ring, meaning you need the entire שחיטה shechita in the right
place. Even though it's כשר kosher when you do only רוב, rov,
if you're doing the whole thing, then the whole thing has to
be done correctly. If you're going to do it, do it correctly.
Okay, ורבי יוסי ברבי יהודה סבר, v'Rebbi Yossi b'Rebbi Yehuda savar, Rebbi
Yossi b'Rebbi Yehuda says no, רוב ככולו, rov k'kulo, once you did
the majority correctly, I don't care what you did after. And as
I said, the conceptual way of explaining this debate, and it comes
up in a number of other פסולי שחיטה, pesulei shechita, is when
we say majority is enough, are we saying all we need is
majority, or are we saying in principle we need the whole thing,
but if you do the majority, we'll consider it like you do
the whole thing? The difference is what in this case? Let's say
you did the whole thing. Do we say anything more than the
majority is irrelevant, the act of שחיטה shechita stopped once you hit
the רוב, rov, or do we say no, רוב rov only was
a, you know, was a substitute, was a stand-in for doing the
whole thing? If you did the whole thing, the whole thing is
considered the act of שחיטה, shechita, and therefore even if you did
the last part incorrectly, it's invalid. So that is the question always
what happens when you do a פסול pasul after the רוב? rov?
Is it a problem or not? It could be about הגרמה, hagrama,
it could be about שהייה, shehiya, it could be about anything. That's
what he's saying the debate is when the invalidity happened, the פסול
pasul happened in the last section. Okay, סבר רוב, savar rov, אבל
aval
let's say it's a different type of a case. הגרים שליש ושחט
שני שליש. Higrim shlish v'shachat shenei shlish.
You started incorrectly. The first third was too high and you finished
it, you did the last two-thirds correctly. Then דברי הכל פסול, divrei
hakol pasul, everybody's going to admit that's invalid. Why? דכי נפיק חיותא,
d'ki nafik chayusa,
once the life of the animal leaves, meaning once you have got
slaughtered the majority of the trachea, so once that has happened, דכי
נפיק חיותא בעינן רוב בשחיטה וליכא, d'ki nafik chayusa ba'inan rov b'shechita
v'leika, you needed the majority of it to have happened with an
act of שחיטה. shechita. So here, if you started too high in
the trachea and then you ended the last two-thirds correctly, once you
got to the majority of the trachea, right, it had not been
done through an act of שחיטה. shechita. When you got to the
majority of the trachea, half had been done through שחיטה shechita and
half had been done through non-שחיטה. shechita. Does everybody get this? So
therefore that is going to be invalid. What he says is the
whole debate is when you did the majority of the שחיטה, shechita,
it was good. Can you ruin it by what you do afterwards?
But if the problem happened earlier on, and by the time the
שחיטה shechita was the majority, it was already had an invalidity, everybody
agrees.
But if you did a sixteenth too high and then went into
the right area, the majority is right...
No, because as soon as you do 51% part of it constitutes
a פסול שחיטה. psul shechita. Okay.
No, but most of it's in the right area.
Doesn't matter. You need every, his argument is when you did 51%
it needs everything
to have been...
Every bit of the majority. Every bit of the majority has to
be כשר. kosher.
Okay, but we're going to have...
So that makes sense. But he says here רוב דשחיטה וליכא. rov
d'shechita v'leika. I know, but it means רוב rov of the סימן.
siman. Okay. So, wait a minute, where are we? חיותא בעינן רוב
בשחיטה וליכא. chayusa ba'inan rov b'shechita v'leika. אמר ליה רב חסדא, amar
lei Rav Chisda, Rav Chisda said to him, אדרבה, adaraba, no, the
opposite. לימא מר איפכא, leima mar ipcha, say the opposite. מחלוקת כשהגרים
שליש ושחט שני שליש. Machlokes k'shehigrim shlish v'shachat shenei shlish. Maybe the
debate is the first third was incorrect and the last two-thirds was
correct. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה סבר, Rebbi Yossi b'Rebbi Yehuda savar, מידי
דהוי אחצי קנה פגום, midi d'hava achatzi kaneh pagum, that Rebbi Yossi
b'Rebbi Yehuda says it's good, why? Because it's the same as if
half of the trachea already had a injury or a neck. Surprisingly
we are going to find out that if the trachea, although often
tiny little holes make things a טריפה, treifa, it depends in what
organ, and we are going to find out that a trachea, as
opposed to the esophagus, can have actually a natural hole or cut
up to half of its width and still a little bit and
got it from half to 51%. That would be a כשר kosher,
*kosher* שחיטה shechita *shechita* because a half it wasn't yet a טריפה
treifa. *treifa*. You now made it 51% a cut טריפה treifa. *treifa*
although you only added 1%. But we actually rule that that's a
כשר kosher. *kosher* שחיטה shechita *shechita*. So he says how is this
any different? If you started too high and you finish in the
right place, why is that worse than if it had a natural
cut in its trachea? Okay. And so okay the first part wasn't
the מעשה שחיטה shechita? *maase shechita*. But when you got to the
51% mark you were doing an act of שחיטה shechita. *shechita*. Okay
so that's that's his argument. And therefore רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi
Yosei be-Rabbi Yehuda? *Reb Yosi b'rebi Yehuda* would say that's good. So
where where were we? מדי דהוה *mideihavei* just like you have a
חצי קנה פגום *chatzi kaneh pagum* if half of the trachea was
already cut there you don't have to do the whole cutting as
an act of שחיטה shechita *shechita* as long as you do the
51% mark. ורבנן V'rabanan, *verabbanan* and the rabbis would say no that's
not good. התם מקום שחיטה hasam makom shechita. הכא לאו מקום שחיטה
hacha lav makom shechita. *hattam makom shechita hacha lav makom shechita*. There's
the cut even though you didn't do it within the right place.
The cut the natural cut in the trachea was in the place
where the act of שחיטה shechita *shechita* has to be done. So
there even though you only did the last 1% what the end
result is that the majority of the trachea was cut where it
needed to be cut. Whereas if you started high and then you
ended in the right place when it got to be 51% cut
the the not the right area was not cut only half of
the right area was cut not the entirety of the right area
was cut. So he says you're right you don't have to do
the whole act. But in the end in the end of the
day it all has the right thing has to be cut. And
when you start too high it's not cut. So that's that debate.
אבל Aval, *aval* where let me just finish the thought אבל שחט
שני שליש והגרים שליש aval shachat shnei shelish v'higrim shelish, *aval shachat
shenei shelish ve-higrim shelish* but the case you said they were debating
like the first two thirds were correct and the last part was
incorrect but you did you know when you got to 51% everything
was perfect דברי הכל כשרה divrei hakol keshera, *divrei hakol keshera* everybody
should agree it's okay דהתנן *de-hatnan* our general principle is רובו של
אחד כמוהו rubo shel echad k'mohu, *rubo shel echad kamoho* that if
you do the majority of a סימן siman. *siman* it counts like
the whole סימן *siman*. So in the end what he is saying
is let us say that everybody agrees and this again for me
it's very interesting because it has much broader implications than just this.
It's a general question of when you say majority do I care
what happens after the majority? So he's arguing maybe everybody would say
what happens after the majority is irrelevant. רובו ככולו rubo k'chulo. *rubo
kekulo* means you've done the majority you're done and if you messed
it up in the last 49% we don't care. The first 51%
was correct everybody agrees. What?
Yes
well okay but presumably even intentional we don't care. We stop after
51%. The whole debate was when the beginning was wrong but by
the time you got to the middle it was right. But if
you did it this way maybe everybody would have agreed it doesn't
matter what happened in the last in the last מיעוט *miyut*. Yes
you have a question.
שחט שני שליש shlish *shachat shenei shelish*.
Yes.
So
what if the animal had a natural hole 50% hole above the
proper place? Yes.
And then you cut down into the 51%?
Yeah or you just ignored it. Ignored that.
Then it would be כשר kosher, *kosher* because then at the end
you have a cut in the right place that goes you know
the רוב rov. *rov*. But here you don't have a cut in
the right place that goes through רוב rov *rov* of the קנה
*kaneh*.
You have a cut high that's not in the right place and
what's going through the right space in the קנה *kaneh* right it's
not going through the majority of it.
And even if you finish so in the end you do have
a cut in the right place you know of the majority of
the קנה *kaneh* by the time the animal has been dead נפקא
חיותא Nafaka Chayuta *nafakeh hiyusa* the life has gone out by the
time the majority is cut at that stage we look at it
we freeze frame it and we look at it and it's not
cut correctly. So that's how he explains.
שחיטה shechita *shechita* again this is my you know ignorance of the
anatomy of the animal but you have the trachea and the esophagus
right? But does it matter which one you start with or? We'll
talk about that.
It might it might that might be the פסול pasul *psul* of
חלדה *chalada* it might be if you do the if you do
the order reverse. We'll talk about that tomorrow. Okay reverse order.
You either stick your knife in the middle of the neck and
go down or you manipulate them and try to move them around
before you did it it would be hard but you could in
theory.
I have another question.
Right they're front and back everybody knows right? You first hit the
trachea and then the esophagus. Okay yes.
And I'm just trying to get because I also hear like there's
a phrase like מקצת היום ככולו mikzas hayom kekulo. *miktzas hayom kekulo*.
Right so yeah you can't universalize but those are questions. For example
I'll just use that as a great example that Michael gives another
example about whether you care about what happens at the end we
do say מקצת היום ככולו k'chulo, *miktzas hayom kekulo*. So for example
a part of a day counts as a whole day in some
areas. So for example I'll give you a relevant example which actually
plays a role in הלכה halacha *halacha* about why women as a
general rule don't go to the מקווה mikvah *mikvah* during the day.
Because for nowadays nowadays we treat the status of you know when
women are נדות *niddas* we basically give them the halachic status as
being like a זבה zavah *zavah* who needs seven clean days. So
seven clean days basically according to the תורה at the beginning of
the seventh day like when somebody finishes excuse the comparison in אבילות
aveilus you get up at the beginning of the seventh day that's
מקצת היום ככולו. So by a זבה zavah the beginning of the
seventh day she can go to the מקווה mikvah already. Why does
why why women go at night? Because if you go to the
מקווה mikvah in the day and then you bleed later that day
so retroactively the going to the מקווה mikvah never counted. Since the
beginning only counts because it's as if the day was done. If
the day actually finished with a bleeding it's the beginning never counted.
And therefore if you go to the מקווה mikvah in the day
and then have sex and then she would bleed later retroactively she
was a זבה the whole time. So therefore we wait till the
go to the going to the מקווה till the night. So that's
a perfect example where we allow the first beginning but only but
what happens later but if later gets messed up it never counted
to begin with. So that is a general question of when you
say a majority counts does it just work because that's all you
need or it works because it's like you did everything but then
what happens later will matter.
Somehow this seems like הגרמה hagrama versus a רוב.
rov I understand it's not always the same הלכה halacha but it
is a general question to ask in all of these areas. Okay
so let's keep on
going. Okay אבל ובקוטא כגובא. aval u'v'kuta k'uba. אמר ליה רב יוסף
amar lei Rav Yosef so רב יוסף Rav Yosef said מאן לימא
לן דהוא רובא דהתם לרבי יוסי בר יהודה קתני לה. man leima
lan dehu ruba dehasam l'Rabbi Yose bar Yehuda kitani lah. No even
though there it says majority is enough which you're reading to mean
once it's a majority we don't care what happens afterwards fine maybe
that's רבי יוסי בר יהודה Rabbi Yose bar Yehuda who says it's
not רבי יוסי בר יהודה? Rabbi Yose bar Yehuda? דילמא רבי יוסי
בר יהודה היא דקתני לה. dilma Rabbi Yose bar Yehuda hi d'katani
lah. Maybe it's רבי יוסי בר יהודה Rabbi Yose bar Yehuda that
says after majority you stop worrying. So אמר ליה אביי amar lei
Abaye so אביי Abaye says and this is sort of like what
Michael was saying you know do we always assume that how we
treat questions of רוב rov is always going to be the same.
אטו כל רובי דאמר רבי יוסי בר יהודה קתני להו? atu kol
rubei d'amar Rabbi Yose bar Yehuda kitani lehu? What anytime you say
majority is enough it's always רבי יוסי בר יהודה? Rabbi Yose bar
Yehuda? I mean we have throughout ש"ס Shas we use a principle
of a majority. So you're going to tell me it's only רבי
יוסי בר יהודה? Rabbi Yose bar Yehuda? So אמר ליה amar lei
he said back no אנא רובי דשחיטה קאמינא. ana rubei de'shechita ka'amina.
No no no but at least within the role of שחיטה shechita.
which was my response to Michael maybe different areas of הלכה halacha
how you deal with the concept of רוב rov changes but at
least by שחיטה shechita. דשמעינן ליה דפליגי. d'shaminnan lei d'pligi. We know
that that is the debate of the Rabbis and רבי יוסי בר
יהודה. Rabbi Yose bar Yehuda. So here we have this question right?
The Rabbis say you can't you have to do it all correctly.
So the question is maybe the Rabbis would agree if you did
the first half correctly I don't care about the last half. Maybe
they agree that רוב rov it's not I don't care what happens
after once you've done the majority what happens later doesn't matter. And
the whole debate is if you started it wrong. That's one way
of reading it. The other way of reading it is that that's
exactly what they debate how do you look at the question of
רוב rov by שחיטה? shechita, Do I רבי יוסי בר יהודה Rabbi
Yose bar Yehuda says after רוב rov I don't care what happens
after and the Rabbis say I always care you know if you're
doing the entire thing. So this famous line that רוב rov?
is enough which the גמרא's Gemara reading to mean you stop worrying
after רוב rov is that only רבי יוסי בר יהודה Rabbi Yose
bar Yehuda or would that even be the Rabbis? Right would the
Rabbis care what happens after רוב?
rov Yes David. I apologize if you've already answered this but is
there a measure of how much how large the incision needs to
be vis-a-vis the neck or vis-a-vis depth? Well no it's only vis-a-vis
the cutting of the trachea and the esophagus. It has to go
in as we've been saying רוב rov which is defined not by
the thickness of the skin you know but by the inner hollow.
So it has to cut through the majority of the inner you
know the inner hollow of the trachea and the esophagus. So you
would basically measure the inner
circle right and it would have to go beyond the center of
the inner circle.
Is that based upon a presumption that that's the amount you need
to cut in order for the animal to die? So that is
an excellent question. We are going to look tomorrow's דף daf and
it's actually going to be quite interesting for people that are interested
about the whole brain death question or whatever about the questions about
you know definition of possible definition of death connected to definitions of
שחיטה. shechita So whether the definition of שחיטה shechita, is about defining
death or not is an open question but I will tell you
one thing to at least problematize that is that by birds we
say you don't have to שחוט shecht both סימנים simanim only one
סימן. So if it was a definition of death it would be
a little strange that we would define death of an animal of
a camel of a cow excuse me different than death of a
bird. But we'll get back to that question. Whether this can be
abstracted to questions about death. Yes. And by רב יוסף Rav Yosef
we could say you could even push or as long as... Well
that's the question. Can you apply the same debate about הגרמה hagrama
to things like שהייה shehiya and דרסה? drasa? Presumably yes if it's
a larger conceptual issue of how do you think what half means
okay but the גמרא Gemara hasn't said that yet. And that issue
will come up later on. Okay the גמרא Gemara has not yet
expanded it. Here it has said שחיטה shechita. which seems to explain
it to all of שחיטה shechita. but the discussion has always been
here about הגרמה. hagrama. You'd be saying that לכתחילה l'chatchila it's okay?
I mean you could always talk about don't fool around because then
you'll come to make the mistake in the beginning but I think
in principle yes. Okay so let's take a look. Okay. Okay, לישנא
אחרינא, Lishna achrina, another way of saying this, which is more or
less the exact same except we just start with the second opinion
first. אמרי, Amrei, they said it. אמר רב הונא אמר רב, Amar
Rav Huna amar Rav, הכי מחלוקת שהגרים שליש ושחט שני שליש, hachi
machlokes she-higrim shelish v'shachat shnei shelish, the debate is that you started
incorrectly, the first third was too high and then the two thirds
were okay. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה סבר מידי דהוה אחתיכה דפגא, Rabbi
Yosei be-Rabbi Yehuda savar midei dahavei achaticha depaga, it's okay as long
as you did the middle correctly, it's like when it started with
a cut in the trachea. ורבנן, and the rabbis would say התם
מקום שחיטה. shechita, No, there at least by the end of the
day, the majority of what was cut was in the right place.
הכא לאו מקום שחיטה. shechitah Here the first part of the cut
was not in the right place and therefore it's no good. אבל,
but that's the debate. אבל שחט שני שליש shlish, והגרים שליש, v'higrim
shelish, if you did the first two thirds correctly and you only
messed it up at the end, דברי הכל כשרה, keshera. then everybody
would say it's fine, we don't care what happened at the end.
דתנן, D'tanan, because we taught רובו של אחד כמוהו, k'mohu the majority
is enough, which we say means and it could be the דיוק
diyuk of the גמרא, Gemara, although I don't know, is not רובו
ככולו. rubo k'chulo So maybe the דיוק diyuk is if it says
רובו ככולו might suggest we actually care about the whole thing. רובו
כמוהו, rubo k'mohu, although you could say כמוהו means ככולו, but maybe
it means רוב rov counts. רוב rov. makes it valid and therefore
we don't care what happens afterwards. רוב rov is the whole requirement.
It's not a stand-in for all of it. מתקיף לה רב חסדא,
Maskif lah Rav Chisda, so רב חסדא Rav Chisda said, מאן לימא
לן דהא רובא דהתם לאו רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה קתני לה? man
leima lan d'ha ruba d'hasam lav Rabbi Yosei be-Rabbi Yehuda katni lah?
Who told you that that statement was even the rabbis? Was not
limited to רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה? Rabbi Yosei be-Rabbi Yehuda דילמא רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה קתני לה, dilma Rabbi Yosei be-Rabbi Yehuda katni lah,
maybe that's only רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yosei be-Rabbi Yehuda? that
is not concerned with anything beyond רוב. rov אמר ליה, Amar lei,
he said back to him, אמר ליה רב יוסף, amar lei Rav
Yosef, אטו כל רובי דאמר רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה קתני להו? atu
kol rubi d'amar Rabbi Yosei be-Rabbi Yehuda katni lehu? Anytime there's any
statement that רוב rov suffices, you're going to say that's just the
position of רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה? Rabbi Yosei be-Rabbi Yehuda Everybody agree
רוב rov works. אמר ליה, Amar lei, no, אנא רובא דשחיטה קאמינא.
ana ruba d'shechita kamina. I meant within the context of שחיטה. shechitah,
דשמעינן להו דפליגי, d'shmeinan lehu d'pligi, there we hear that they debate
with the rabbis so yes. Meaning, maybe different areas of הלכה halacha?
how you deal with רוב rov differ, but now we're talking within
שחיטה. shechitah. Within שחיטה, shechita. does רוב rov count as a stand-in
for all of it? But if you did all of it, I
care what you did at the last part. Or do I just
care about רוב rov and I don't care what you did at
the last part? So that is either, so we don't know, that's
either the debate of רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yosei be-Rabbi Yehuda
and the rabbis, or they all agree that I don't care about
the last part and the only issue
here was when you started incorrectly. But now we're going to do
a couple of variations about how you're doing this act, which part
of it was correct, which was not correct. Let's take a look.
הגרים שליש ושחט שליש והגרים שליש. higrim shelish v'shachat shelish v'higrim shelish.
This is even worse than the case before. The case that we
said at most we said רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yosei be-Rabbi
Yehuda would say okay, is the top third was incorrect, the last
two thirds were okay. Let's say you only did the critical middle
correct.
The majority of the act of שחיטה shechita was done
incorrectly, but the cutting of the middle of the trachea was correct.
You started too high, you dropped down, you cut the middle of
the trachea, and then you ended too high. Okay? So two-thirds of
the cut was in the wrong place. Only one third of the
cut was in the right place, but it was right at the
middle. It got the middle part of the trachea. Does that count?
Okay, presumably this is a question within רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi
Yosei be-Rabbi Yehuda, that allows you not to have to do it
all correct. רב הונא אמר רב כשרה, Rav Huna amar Rav keshera,
so רב הונא Rav Huna says in the name of רב Rav
it's כשרה. keshera? רב יהודה אמר רב טרפה, Rav Yehuda amar Rav
tereifa, so רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said in the name of רב
Rav it's טרפה. tereifa. So the debate here seems to be do
we care about the act of שחיטה, shechita. the cut, or the
majority of the cut, or do we actually care about cutting the
middle of the trachea? Now we're going to really only didn't cut
the majority. Exactly, even though you did not cut the majority. רב
הונא אמר רב כשרה, Rav Huna amar Rav keshera, and it's going
to explain it. Why is it כשרה? keshera, כי נפק חיותא בשחיטה
קנפק, ki nafak chayusa b'shechita k'nafak, when the life leaves, and here's
David's point about defining death, which is something that we will get
back to. For now, we're going to just notice. When the life
leaves, when you cut the middle of the trachea, you're doing it
with an act of שחיטה. shechita So as long as that middle
part was done correctly, you're fine. רב יהודה אמר רב טרפה. Rav
Yehuda amar Rav tereifa. No, it's invalid. בעינן רובא בשחיטה וליכא. ba'inan
ruba b'shechita v'leika. You need most of the trachea cut through an
act of שחיטה. shechita, It's not just the middle has to be
cut through an act of שחיטה, shechita, you need most of the
trachea cut. So now we're going to do the mirror image of
this debate. שחט שליש, shachat shelish, let's say the first third was
correct, והגרים שליש, the middle third was too high, ושחט שליש, v'shachat
shelish, and the last third was correct. So that should be the
exact reverse, right? Because there the middle section was not done correctly,
but the majority of the cut was done correctly. So the positions
should reverse themselves and they indeed do. Does everybody get that? Right?
The middle, the first third of the cut that you said if
you pre-frame as a 51 percent was in the wrong place. Yeah,
but at the end it's okay. Oh, so you're saying that according
to רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, if we stop at the רוב rov
issue, right, why don't we just stop at the רוב rov and
say it's not good? Well maybe he only says you stop at
the רוב rov when it's כשרה, keshera because then you've already once
you've already said it's כשרה kasher. you don't worry about. what happens
afterwards. If it's not yet כשר, kosher. you can maybe still make
it כשר. kosher. It's a good point. I, you know, do we,
we don't apply the stopping at the רוב necessarily in both directions.
So let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara assumes very good point
by James but the גמרא Gemara assumes that this is the exact
flip of, mirror of the other case. Wait, so the same? Yes.
I'm not sure the math works. Where, where, how you measuring רוב
from the beginning of the cut? The depth into the hollow of
the, of the, what do you call it? Of the trachea. Trachea.
But it's שליש and שליש, right? Good and bad. If the first
is, the first is no good in this case, the first is
good in this case. In this case we're on right now? Yes,
it started good, the middle section, which was when you got to
the middle of the trachea was too high, and then it ended
good. But the middle section is only 17 percent. Correct. And you've
already got 33 percent. Right. So your majority good. No, not the
majority of the width. If this is, if this represents, this stage
represents the hollow of the trachea, okay, and this line here is
exactly the 50 percent line. So, a normal שחיטה shechita. has to
go beyond this, right? It has to cut through half of it.
I did this part good. I got up here, and then I
ended here good. Okay? So, the majority of the trachea was cut
with an act of שחיטה, shechita? but the 51 percent line was
not crossed at an act of שחיטה. shechita, It was crossed up
here. So you're not... you're in the bad section. In your majority.
No, I'm actually putting the, only the first
17 out of 33, the top half... yeah... of the bad section.
Right. I go up here. I did 33 percent. I go up
here. Okay, it's bad. So, you're saying, yes, stop right, right at
the 51 percent. Right, right, right above the line, but I'm up
here too high. Yeah. So, I've had 33 percent good and 17
percent bad. Right. The majority of that cut is good. Oh, you
can't do a double majority. We're only allowing the majority of the
trachea. You can't then do within that freeze-frame... okay, now it goes
back to depth. Right, right. Okay, but you're not doing a, you
can't do a double majority. We're saying you can do a majority
of the trachea, but that then has to be done, actually has
to be cut correctly. You can't do a majority of the majority.
So in this case the majority has been cut correctly because you
were good and good in the... the majority of the trachea has
been cut correctly, but the middle of the trachea has not been
cut correctly. And where is the life...? That's the question. The assumption
is that once you get to the middle of the trachea, you
pass the middle of the trachea, it's like its life force,
its חיות, chiyut, as נפש חיות nefesh chiyut is gone. But that
was the chest. Yes. You could... okay. That was just you could
start bad and then... so that's what we said. Start bad, do
this part correct, and end bad, and there was an opinion that
that's okay because you cut that middle line correctly. Now we're flipping
it. Okay, and it still seems that he needs a majority to
be cut correctly. He did do a majority correctly, just not the
middle line. I don't see, I still don't see how one could
say... because the other one is saying you do not
need to cut the majority of the trachea correctly, you just need
to cut the middle of the trachea correctly. That's the debate.
Do you need to cut the majority correctly, or do you need
to cut the middle of the trachea correctly?
Okay, and that was the, the first position would be if you
cut and end bad, right, cross the middle line
good, you're fine, so
that it's only one third good.
Right. You're still fine. Right. Because it's not about cutting the majority
of
the trachea, it's about
cutting the middle of the trachea.
And the other opinion says it's about cutting the majority. So he
said משהו על פני רובו mashu al pnei ruvo doesn't mean cutting
the majority correctly but just getting...
yeah, well now we're getting, right, correct. I mean 51 percent, yeah.
I mean according to that opinion. So let's take a look. Okay.
So, where
are we? Okay.
הגרים שליש ושחט שליש והגרים שליש higrim shlish v'shachat shlish v'higrim shlish
we just did that below. שחט שליש והגרים שליש ושחט שליש. shachat
shlish v'higrim shlish v'shachat shlish. Okay, the first third correct, the middle
third not, the bottom third correct. רב יהודה אמר רב כשרה. Rav
Yehuda amar Rav kesherah. It's כשר, kosher, okay, because it is the,
he basically he's reversing himself. Before he said פסול pasul because he
cared not about the middle line but about the actual trachea itself.
And so here he's saying it's כשר. kasher אתו שיילוהו לרב הונא.
ato she'iluhi l'Rav Huna. They asked רב הונא Rav Huna who debated
him before. אמר להו טרפה. amar lehu tereifah. So he said it's
טרפה. tereifah. So everybody kept their position but reversed
themselves because this was
a reverse
case. שמע רב יהודה איקפיד.
shama Rav
Yehuda ikpid.
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda heard that רב הונא Rav Huna was reversing
him, or arguing differently, and he got upset. He took it personally.
אמר טרפנא ומכשר. amar tarafna u'machshar. When I say it's טרפה tereifah
he says it's כשר. kasher, ומכשרנא, u'machsharna, when I say it's כשר,
kasher.
טריף, tarif, he says it's טרפה. tereifah. So אמר ליה רב הונא,
amar lei Rav Huna, so רב הונא Rav Huna said, שפיר קא
מקפיד. shapir ka makpid. It's, you know, he was right to be
offended.
Why? Why not?
I mean, it seems we're being consistent. Why should he all of
a sudden take offense?
So first of all, again we get back to the question about
authority.
חדא איהו שמיע ליה מיניה דרב ואנא לא שמיע לי. chada ihu
shmia lei minei d'Rav v'ana la shmia li. If you remember the
first debate, they were debating what רב Rav.
said about the case.
One was אמר רב יהודה אמר רב
amar
Rav
Yehuda amar Rav and the other was אמר רב הונא אמר רב.
amar Rav Huna amar Rav. Here, right, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said
his, both of his positions in the name of רב. Rav I
only said my second position on my own derivation.
I did not have רב's Rav authority.
So that's number one, he was upset because he had a tradition
of רב and I did not. ועוד Ve'od and secondly, האיכא רובא
בשחיטה. Ha'ika ruba b'shchita. How could I say that this case is
no good? In truth, in this case, a majority is being shechted
correctly. Now obviously the answer is, but who cares? For you, that's
not the issue, the issue is the middle line. So the גמרא
Gemara is going to try to tell רב הונא Rav Huna don't
reverse yourself so quickly. אמר ליה רב חסדא, Amar lei Rav Chisda,
רב חסדא Rav Chisda said to רב הונא, Rav Huna, לא תהדר
בך, Lo teihadar bach, don't go so quick to reverse yourself. You
have a very nice position and if you reverse yourself here, דאם
כן מסתרת לה לקמייתא. d'im kein masatart la l'kamaitha. If you reverse
yourself in this case, you're going to implicitly give up your first
position because your first position when you said it was כשר kasher
was based on the fact that you cared about the middle line.
So here, which is the reverse, you should say it's פסול pasul.
and if you don't say it here, you're going to have, you're
going to effectively reverse yourself on your first position. התם מאי טעמא
מכשרת, Hatam mai ta'ama machshart, why did you say the middle third
was okay? דכי נפק חיותא בהכשר קנפיק, d'ki nafak chayuta b'hechsher kanafik,
when the life went out, when you got to the fifty-one percent
line, you were doing it in the act of שחיטה. shechita. Even
though the שחיטה shechita. did not cut the majority of the trachea,
but the fifty-one percent line was cut, was cut correctly. הכא נמי,
Hacha nami, so here, which is the reverse case, כי נפק חיותא
באגרמה קנפיק, ki nafak chayuta b'agrama kanafik, the middle third is in
the wrong place, so when that midline is passed, then it's being
done with a non-valid act of שחיטה. shechita. It's being done with
an אגרמה. agrama. So you need to be consistent. Don't back down.
Stick to your guns. Your position is not how much of the
trachea you're cutting but whether you're cutting the middle of the trachea
correctly. So the same way you said if the middle was okay
I don't care about the beginning and the end, say the reverse:
if the beginning and end is okay and the middle was not
good, it's going to be invalid. Okay, so we have that debate.
איקלע רב נחמן לסורא. Ikla Rav Nachman l'Sura. Is he going to
run his own? I guess, I don't know, it's a good question.
Maybe it's sort of like what James said, that you could sort
of say you need both criteria, you need both two-thirds and the
middle, I mean, there's ways or, no, excuse me, both would be
the opposite. There's ways of making hybrids of the two. Is the
גמרא Gemara going to come to a conclusion or? Sort of, not
really. איקלע רב נחמן לסורא, Ikla Rav Nachman l'Sura, so רב נחמן
came to סורא, Sura, בעו מיניה, ba'u minei, and they asked him
the following question: שחט שליש והגרים שליש ושחט שליש מאי? Shachat shlish
v'higrim shlish v'shachat shlish mai? You can tell they're having fun, okay.
This is where, right, exactly, this is where it gets to be
hypothetical. So they asked him exactly this case: first third good, middle
not good, last third good. What's the הלכה? halacha אמר להו, Amar
lehu, לאו היינו דרבי אלעזר בר מניומי? lav hainu d'Rabbi Elazar bar
Minyumi? Isn't this the position of רבי אלעזר בר מניומי? Rabbi Elazar
bar Minyumi? How? דאמר ר' אלעזר בר מניומי, D'amar Rabbi Elazar bar
Minyumi, רבי אלעזר בר מניומי Rabbi Elazar bar Minyumi said שחיטה העשויה
כמסרק, shechita ha'asuyah k'masreik, if the שחיטה shechita is like a comb,
I don't know where exactly the comb example is, but it basically
means up and down and up and down, I guess if you
jag it. So here too it's sort of jagged, it's going, this
and higher and lower. Okay. כשירה, kesheira, it's כשר, kasher. so here
too it's כשר. kasher. The גמרא Gemara says no, ודילמא במקום שחיטה?
u'dilma b'makom shechita? Maybe that means that if you did jagged but
it was all within the kosher zone? It doesn't have to be
a straight line, but it's all in the kosher zone. That doesn't
tell us our case where it's not all in the kosher zone.
So the גמרא Gemara says במקום שחיטה מאי למימרא? b'makom shechita mai
l'meimra? What would be the חידוש chiddush if it's all in the
kosher zone? No, מהו דתימא, mahu d'teima, I might have thought בעינן
שחיטה מפורעת, ba'inan shechita mefura'at, maybe you need an exposed שחיטה, shechita
maybe you need a straight line where you know you can look
and see the entire cut without it being some of it hidden
because it's higher or lower and you don't get a straight eyesight
on the entire cut, you need an entire exposed שחיטה, shechita. קא
משמע לן ka mashma lan that you don't. So yes, up and
down is fine if it's in the kosher zone. We don't know
about if it's in the non-kosher zone. Okay, so we're not done,
we're going to keep on playing with this. יתיב רבי אבא אחוריה
דרב כהנא, Yativ Rabbi Abba achorei d'Rav Kahana, so רבי אבא Rabbi
Abba was sitting behind רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, ויתיב רב כהנא קמיה
דרב יהודה, v'yativ Rav Kahana kimei d'Rav Yehuda, and רב כהנא Rav
Kahana was sitting in front of רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. Meaning רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda was giving the שיעור, shiur, רב כהנא Rav Kahana
was in the front row, and רבי אבא Rabbi Abba was in
the back row. ויתיב וקאמר, V'yativ v'ka'amar, and רב כהנא Rav Kahana
asked רב יהודה Rav Yehuda the following question: שחט שליש והגרים שליש
ושחט שליש מאי? Shachat shlish v'higrim shlish v'shachat shlish mai? Same thing.
First third correct, middle third bad, last third correct. What's the law?
אמר ליה, Amar lei, שחיטתו כשירה. shechitatu kesheira. He said it's כשר
kasher. because you look at not the midline but you look at
the majority of the, of the trachea. So how about the reverse?
הגרים שליש ושחט שליש והגרים שליש מאי? Higrim shlish v'shachat shlish v'higrim
shlish mai? What about beginning and end were no good, the middle
was good? אמר ליה, שחיטתו פסולה. Amar lei shechitatu psula, It's פסול.
pasul? Again, consistent. We don't care about the midline, we care about
the trachea. Okay. שחט במקום נקב מהו? Shachat b'makom nekaiv mahu? Let's
say there was already a cut in the trachea and you just
finished the job. What's the law? אמר ליה, Amar lei, שחיטתו כשירה.
shechitatu kesheira. That's כשר. kasher? So that's by the way a bit
of a surprise because you would think if it's about the midline,
then I understand. If it naturally got a cut and it got
me to the midline without me having to cut, fine. It's all
about cutting at the midline. But if it's about doing the actual
cutting correctly, so maybe I could not. Presumably the way this is
being conceptualized as we'll see more in a minute is that if
the cut already exists, so I define the trachea differently. I define
the trachea more by what's left since the cut is already there.
And that allows me to only cut a little and not have
to cut a lot. So he says, that's כשר. kasher שחט ופגע
בו נקב מהו? Shachat upaga bo nekev mahu? Let's say you, let's
say the cut was in the back of the trachea. So you
שחטד shechted and let's say the cut was exactly to the midpoint.
So you שחטד shechted and then you hit the back cut of
the trachea. What's the law? אמר ליה Amar lei, שחיטתו פסולה, shechitatu
pesula. it's invalid. Wait, so what was the problem? So the first
case is the cut was in both cases the cut was halfway
through the trachea. In the first case it was in the front
of the trachea, so you added a little bit and got it
over the midline, that's כשר. kasher In the other case it's the
back of the trachea, trachea, and you cut and then once you
got to the midpoint you connected with the, so why's it פסול?
So presumably, well first of all, one thing to note is in
the first case you actually crossed the midline. In this case you
didn't cross the midline, you only got up to the midline. But
let's see how the גמרא's Gemara going to ask that question. So
let's take a look. So אזל רבי אבא. Azal Rabbi Abba. Rabbi
Abba who was in the back row, he went. אזל רבי אבא
אמר קמיה דרבי אלעזר. Azal Rabbi Abba amar kamei d'Rabbi Elazar. He
told it over to Rabbi Elazar. אזל רבי אלעזר אמר קמיה דרבי
יוחנן, Azal Rabbi Elazar amar kamei d'Rabbi Yochanan, this distinction. So אמר
ליה מאי שנא? Amar lei mai shna? So Rabbi Yochanan said to
Rabbi Elazar, how do you explain the difference between whether the cut
is in the front or the back? אמר ליה, Amar lei, שחט
במקום נקב, shachat bimkom nekev, if the cut was in the beginning,
נעשה כמי ששחט עובד כוכבים וגמר ישראל. na'aseh k'mi sheshachat oved kochavim
v'gamar Yisrael. It's like a non-Jew started and a Jew finished. Okay,
the first half wasn't good, but it wasn't yet an act of
שחיטה. shechita You did the last half, means you cut through the
midpoint, so as long as you're cutting through the midpoint you're fine.
So who cares if the cut's in the front but you cut
through the midpoint, you're fine. Wait, even if you didn't do the
majority of the שחיטה? Correct. I know, it's not consistent with the
other part, which is the problem, but let's just finish this. שחט
ופגע בו נקב, Shachat upaga bo nekev, if however you were cutting
and then you encountered the cut and the cut was halfway from
the back, so you never cut the midpoint, right? נעשה כמי ששחט
ישראל וגמר עובד כוכבים. na'aseh k'mi sheshachat Yisrael v'gamar oved kochavim. It's
like a Jew שחטד, shechted, began the שחיטה, and the non-Jew finished,
meaning the midpoint from midpoint on it was not being done by
you, and the midpoint is the point that matters. Okay, so therefore
it's not good. So that's the difference. So קרי ליה kari lei
Rabbi Yochanan did not like this answer, so he said to him,
עובד כוכבים עובד כוכבים, oved kochavim oved kochavim, goy, goy, don't tell
me about this stuff. So רש"י's Rashi made a point of saying
it's not like he called Rabbi Elazar a non-Jew. What he meant
was it was more a mocking statement. You can tell me all
day, oh it's like a goy, it's like a goy, all day,
that's a bad analogy, don't tell me that, that's not a good
analogy. Why not? אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so Rava says, שפיר קרי
ליה עובד כוכבים עובד כוכבים. shapir kari lei oved kochavim oved kochavim.
It was good that he taunted him, that he made fun. It
wasn't a good analogy. בשלמא התם, bishlama hatam, there's a difference. In
the case of the non-Jew, מדאית ליה לישראל למשחט רובא ולא שחט,
mid'it lei l'Yisrael l'mishchat ruba v'lo shachat, since the Jew should have
שחטד shechted the majority and he didn't, the non-Jew, you know, picked
up after fifty percent and finished it off, כי נפקי חיותא בידא
דעובד כוכבים קא נפקי. ki nafki chiyuta b'yada d'oved kochavim ka nafki.
When the life is going out, it's going out through the act
of the non-Jew. If the non-Jew finishes, the non-Jew cuts the fifty-one
percent line and that's being done by a non-Jew. אלא הכא, ela
hacha, here, מכדי שוחט שחיט ליה, michdee shocheit shachit lei, you did
the whole act, there was no other act being done. מה לי
במקום נקב מה לי פגע בו נקב? ma li bimkom nekev ma
li paga bo nekev? What do I care if the whole started,
what do I care if the whole ended? Now personally, okay, basically
what it's saying is nobody else is doing the act, so it
should be incorporated into your act of שחיטה. Now that actually makes
sense because Mikael had been picking up that there's a logical problem
here. This is the same position that the first half of his
teaching was, I don't care who did the majority of the cutting,
I care where the midline was. Right, remember? Or was he the
opposite way, which one was he? He says שחט שליש והגרים שליש
ושחט שליש, shachat shlish v'higrim shlish v'shachat shlish, no, I'm sorry, the
opposite. He says I don't care about the midline, he says I
care about the majority of the cutting. So if he doesn't care
about the midpoint, he cares about the majority of the cutting, then
even the first case doesn't make sense. If the first half was
naturally cut and you just added a quarter of an inch, you
didn't do the majority of the cutting, right? So how come that's
כשר? kasher He doesn't say you have to do the whole thing,
how come that's כשר kasher if he cares not about the midpoint?
So it seems like the logic is that you are incorporating the
existing cut into your act. Since it's not being done by somebody
else and I'm continuing it, so it's like that becomes part of
my act. So he says if that's the case, then it shouldn't
matter if it's the front cut or the back cut. Either way,
if you're doing it and nobody else is doing it, it gets
incorporated into your act. So that presumably explains it because, yes, there
is a logical problem. Why does it suffice if I just cut
the middle, given that, given that for him, it's not the midline
that matters, but it's the majority of the cutting? But here you
have a very fascinating conceptual debate of whether we care about the
majority of the cutting of the trachea or whether it's the cutting
of the midline, and the phrase נפקא חיותא is very important, because
that will get us to the discussion tomorrow, which is really a
discussion about, you know, about thinking about, like, life and death and
how do you define it. You see what the הלכה halacha is,
what, you know, no. So let's just read, I know we're with...
it's... I just want to get a little bit further. Let's just
read the משנה, mishna, okay? Or see, see what we can do
in the next five minutes. השוחט מן הצדדים, Ha-shochet min ha-tzdadim, next
phase... alright, let's say you shecht not, you know, we've been talking
about shechting here and you can't shecht from the back because you'll
break the neck and the spine and make it a טריפה. What
about if you shecht at the side? So that actually we're going
to see is okay because you'll get to the trachea and the
esophagus and it won't be through breaking the... there's not a הלכה
that you can't do it in the back. The problem is that
if you do it in the back, you break... I'm sorry, if
you do it in the back, you break the spine. So if
you... so the גמרא Gemara will even talk about yanking the trachea
and the esophagus behind the spine and shechting them from the back.
So it's not really about front or back, it's about not hitting
the spine. So let's take a look. השוחט מן הצדדים, Ha-shochet min
ha-tzdadim, if you shecht from the side of the neck, שחיטתו כשרה,
shechitato keshera, כשרה. kasher, המולק מן הצדדים, Ha-molek min ha-tzdadim, remember מליקה
melika is what the כהן kohen does with his fingernail to bird
sacrifices and he does it from the back. So there specifically he's
supposed to pierce the back of the neck, the spine. So there
it's the opposite is true. מליקתו פסולה, Melikato pesula, the side is
not good. He has to be cutting through the back, the spine.
השוחט מן העורף, Ha-shochet min ha-oref, if you shecht from the very
back of the neck, the spine, שחיטתו פסולה, shechitato pesula, it's invalid
because it makes it a טריפה. המולק מן העורף, Ha-molek min ha-oref,
of course if you do מליקה melika from the back, from the
spine, מליקתו כשרה, melikato keshera, כשרה, that's exactly how it's supposed to
be. השוחט מן הצוואר, Ha-shochet min ha-tzavar, so we've talked about the
side and the back, now we're going to be talking about the
front. If you shecht from the neck itself, obviously שחיטתו כשרה, shechitato
keshera, that's your classic שחיטה. המולק מן הצוואר, Ha-molek min ha-tzavar, if
you do מליקה melika from the front, מליקתו פסולה, melikato pesula, it's
invalid. שכל העורף כשר למליקה, She-kol ha-oref kasher le-melika, the entire back
of the neck is כשר for מליקה, melika, וכל הצוואר כשר לשחיטה,
ve-kol ha-tzavar kasher le-shechita, the entire throat which includes the sides, it
doesn't say but it includes the sides, is כשר for שחיטה. So
שחיטה is the throat and the sides, מליקה melika is the back
of the neck. נמצא, Nimtza,
so what you conclude from this is: כשר בשחיטה פסול במליקה, Kasher
be-shechita pasul be-melika, what's כשר
for שחיטה is invalid for מליקה, melika, the throat and the sides;
כשר במליקה פסול בשחיטה, Kasher be-melika pasul be-shechita, what's valid for מליקה,
melika, which is the back of the neck, is invalid for שחיטה.
And this is going to lead to a whole series of משניות
mishnayot of things that are like mutually exclusive categories, okay? So we
will pick up here tomorrow discussing שחיטה and מליקה. melika.